There are lots of good reasons
to try and follow a healthier diet—
you lose weight,
you feel good,
but the main reason?
To live a longer, happier,
more productive life.
Welcome to the
NutritionFacts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today, we look at bone
mineral density screening,
the safety and efficacy of
oral and injective medications,
which foods may protect
our bones, and more.
Nearly one in five adults in the world may
have osteoporosis—that's hundreds of millions
of people. The word "osteoporosis"
literally means porous bone. Now,
most of our bone is actually porous to begin
with. Bone mineral density is considered to
be the standard measure for the diagnosis of
osteoporosis, although the bone mineral density
cutoff for an osteoporosis diagnosis is kind
of arbitrary. Using the standard definition,
osteoporosis may affect about one in 10
women by age 60, two in 10 by age 74,
and six or seven out of 10 by age 90. Osteoporosis
is typically thought of as a disease in women,
but one-third of hip fractures occur in
men. The lifetime risk for osteoporotic
fractures for 50-year-old white women and men
is 40% and 13.3% respectively. The good news
is that osteoporosis need not occur. Based on a
study of the largest twin registry in the world,
less than 30% of osteoporotic fracture risk is
heritable, leading the researchers to conclude
prevention of fractures, even in the oldest
elderly, should focus on lifestyle interventions.
This is consistent with the enormous variation
of hip fracture rates around the world,
with the incidence of hip fracture varying
tenfold or even a hundredfold between countries,
suggesting that excessive bone loss is not
just an inevitable consequence of aging.
The United States Preventive Services Task
Force, an independent scientific panel
that sets evidence-based clinical prevention
guidelines, recommends osteoporosis screening,
such as DEXA bone mineral density scan, for all
women aged 65 and older, and potentially starting
even earlier than 65 for women at increased
risk, such as those with a parental history
of hip fracture, smokers, excessive alcohol
consumers, or those with low body weight.
What should you do if you're diagnosed,
or more importantly, what should you do
to never be diagnosed? Before exploring
the drugs offered to treat osteoporosis,
there are some drugs that may cause it. So
let's start there. Stomach acid-blocking
proton pump inhibitor drugs, so-called
PPIs with brand names like Prilosec,
Prevacid, Nexium, Protonix, and AcipHex, are
among the most popular drugs in the world,
raking in billions of dollars a year. But then
in 2006, two observational studies out of Europe
suggested an association between intake of
this class of drugs and increased risk of
hip fracture. By 2010, the growing evidence
forced the US Food and Drug Administration
to issue a safety alert implicating PPI use with
fractures of the hip, wrist, and spine. By now,
there have been dozens of such studies involving
more than two million people that overall show
higher hip fracture rates among both long-
and short-term users at all dose levels.
The irony is that most people taking these
drugs shouldn't even be on them in the first
place. These PPIs are only FDA approved for
10 days of use for the treatment of H. pylori,
up to two weeks for heartburn, up to 8 weeks for
acid reflux disease, and for two to six months for
ulcers. Yet, in a community survey, most users
remained on these drugs for more than a year,
and more than 60% of patients were taking them for
inappropriate reasons, often wrongly prescribed
for "indigestion," for instance. Calls to stop
this massive overuse from regulatory authorities
have fallen on deaf doctor ears, and now
that they're available over the counter,
the problem of overuse may have just gotten
even worse. They can be hard to stop taking
since many patients experience withdrawal
symptoms that can last for weeks. In fact,
if you take normal healthy volunteers without
any symptoms and put them on these drugs for
2 months and then covertly switch them
to a placebo without their knowledge,
all of a sudden they can develop acid-related
symptoms such as heartburn or acid regurgitation,
ending up worse off than they were before
they even started taking the drugs.
In addition to bone fractures, this class
of drugs has also been linked to increased
risk of other possible long-term
adverse effects, such as pneumonia,
intestinal infections, kidney failure, stomach
cancer, and cardiovascular disease. In fact,
the blood vessel effects could explain
the case report of abrupt onset profound
erectile dysfunction in a healthy young man
after initiating over-the-counter Prilosec
and also premature death. There are individuals
with conditions like Zollinger-Ellison syndrome,
stricken with tumors that can cause
excess stomach acid secretion,
for whom the risk versus benefit of long-term use
may be acceptable. But that's a far cry from the
hundred million PPIs prescribed annually in the
United States alone to deal with acid reflux.
Without drugs, recommendations include weight
loss, smoking cessation, avoiding fatty meals,
especially within 2 to 3 hours of
bedtime, increased fiber consumption,
and an overall more plant-based
diet because non-vegetarianism
is associated with twice the odds of
acid reflux-induced inflammation. Other
classes of drugs associated with hip
fracture risk include antidepressants,
antiparkinson's drugs, antianxiety drugs,
oral corticosteroids, and the other major
class of heartburn drugs, the H2 blockers
such as Pepcid, Zantac, Tagamet, and Axid.
Excessive bone loss is not just an
inevitable consequence of aging,
and one of the things we can do to lower
our risk and that of our patients is to
take into account the potential skeletal side
effects of the drugs we take and prescribe.
What about the drugs prescribed to treat
osteoporosis? First, let me address efficacy.
Drug therapy for osteoporosis is recommended
for those 50 and older with a history of past
hip or spine fractures, those with hip or spine
T-scores of -2.5 or less, and postmenopausal
women or men aged 50 and older who don't meet that
cutoff but have an estimated 20% or higher risk of
major osteoporotic fracture over the subsequent
decade or an estimated 3% or greater risk of hip
fracture. Specifically, a T-score is a measure of
how dense your bones are compared to a 30-year-old
white woman, since that's the standard. We tend
to lose bone as we age. You can be labeled as
having osteoporosis even if you have completely
normal bone density for your age. Of course,
just because your bone density may be normal
doesn't mean it's necessarily optimal,
which is why the National Osteoporosis
Foundation set out these guidelines for
drug treatment. Though another reason, perhaps,
is because it gets substantial funding from the
drug industry which rakes in literally billions
of dollars in profits from osteoporosis drugs.
What does the science say? The primary drug class
used to treat osteoporosis is the bisphosphonates
sold under brand names such as Fosamax, Actonel,
Boniva, and Reclast. They're most effective at
reducing vertebral fractures, cutting the
risk in postmenopausal women from 2.8% down
to 1.44%. That's a relative risk reduction of
50% but an absolute risk reduction of only 1.4%,
meaning you'd have to treat 71 women to
prevent just one woman from getting a
vertebral fracture. Unfortunately, the diagnosis
of vertebral fracture is kind of wishy-washy,
and depending on how you define the changes on
an x-ray, the prevalence of vertebral fractures
can vary as much as 3% to 90% in the same elderly
population—almost none to almost all. They're all
so poorly predictive of back pain or disability.
Vertebral fractures can certainly lead to back
pain and reduced physical function, but only
about a third are symptomatic at all. The most
harmful fractures are hip fractures. Despite most
of the clinical trials for osteoporosis treatment
being funded by the drug companies themselves, no
primary prevention benefit from bisphosphonates
has been found for hip fractures. In other words,
taking these drugs has not been convincingly shown
to prevent fracturing your hip in the first place.
However, having a prior fracture doubles your risk
of breaking another bone, so for those at high
risk, these bisphosphonate drugs may decrease
the odds of hip fracture by 25%. So, the absolute
risk reduction is again only about 1%. It may take
treating 91 people for 3 years to prevent one
hip fracture. An overconfidence in the power of
pills and procedures for disease prevention may
be one of the reasons doctors and patients alike
may undervalue diet and lifestyle approaches. In a
study of those undergoing bone density scans, the
average yearly fracture risk that would motivate
most participants to consider preventive medicine
was 50% to 60%, much higher than their actual
risk. Most patients want to be told the truth;
they want to be told what the chances are that
the drugs will actually benefit them. But there's
a tension between the patient's right to know
and the likely reduction in their willingness
to take the drug if they knew the truth. In
the bone density scan survey, participants
greatly overestimate their own personal risk for
hip fracture, thinking it was around 19% over
the next 5 years, which is more than 10 times
higher than their actual risk of 1.4%. Rather
than disabusing them of this overestimate, some
suggest physicians should do the opposite—stoke
fear in patients who refuse to comply with
medication recommendations by increasing their
perceived susceptibility to fragility fractures
as well as their perceived severity of suffering
from a fragility fracture. Since emotion can
be more motivating than reason and anecdotal
evidence can be more effective than evidence, a
graphic scenario of suffering and incapacitation
after hip fracture will enhance emotional
perception of this threat. But hip fractures
can indeed be devastating and are associated
with a significant risk of ensuing death.
So, what about all the lives these drugs must be
saving? Well, only about a quarter of the deaths
following fractures may be attributable to the
fracture itself, so most of the mortality risk may
just be a consequence of the comorbidities—that
is, the other diseases and poor health status—of
people who tend to fracture their hips. So, they
might have died anyway in that same timeframe
even if they hadn't broken any bone. This may
help explain why osteoporosis drug treatments,
particularly bisphosphonates, fail to
significantly reduce overall mortality.
Okay, so the efficacy of the primary
drug class used to treat osteoporosis
is so slight on an individual basis that
most patients, if truly fully informed,
likely would not take them. And that's
before even talking about the side effects,
which I'll turn to right now. Potential lack of
efficacy is not the only reason why most people
prescribed bisphosphonate drugs for osteoporosis
like Fosamax, Actonel, Boniva, and Reclast,
may stop taking them within a year. They're too
rare but devastating side effects—osteonecrosis
of the jaw and atypical femur fractures—that
contributed to around a 50% drop in the use
of this class of drugs when they came to light.
The New York Times article noting the decline
explained the reasoning: reports of the drugs
causing jawbones to rot and thigh bones to snap
in two have shaken many osteoporosis patients
so much that they say they would rather take
their chances with the disease. The jaw rot
syndrome that prevents many from initiating
treatment for fear of their jaw falling off can
severely impact many aspects of quality of life
but is exceedingly rare, affecting at most one
in a thousand patients treated for osteoporosis.
Atypical femur fractures can occur more frequently
though, as many as one in 300 users treated for 3
years. They're called atypical because
they occur not after a fall or trauma,
but just during routine activities
like walking, twisting at the waist,
or even just standing still. Your femur, your
thigh bone, the biggest bone in your body,
just breaks in half—too cruel an irony from
a drug that's supposed to protect your bones.
These bisphosphonates work by inhibiting
the action of a type of bone cell called
osteoclasts. Your entire skeleton is constantly
being remodeled, with bone added in some spots
and taken away in others to conform to changing
demand. The cells that are continually laying
down new bone are called osteoblasts,
and the ones that chisel away old bone
are called osteoclasts. It makes sense then that
curbing the osteoclasts could prevent bone loss,
but by reducing the active remodeling process,
the bisphosphonates can freeze the skeleton,
allowing for the accumulation of microcracks
over time, resulting in stress fractures.
Other osteoporosis drugs, like denosumab, sold as
Prolia, prevent the same formation of osteoclasts
in the first place and have been plagued by the
same kinds of rare but disturbing side effects. As
with anything in life, it all comes down to risks
versus benefits. I mean, how many hip fractures
are prevented for every femur that snaps? It
depends on your race and how long you're on
these drugs. After 5 years, in white women, 36
hip fractures are prevented for every atypical
femur fracture. Hispanic women only get half
the benefit, about 18 to 1, and for Asian women,
it's only about five hip fractures prevented for
every femur fracture caused. The study claims it
failed to accrue enough data on black women. At
10 years of drug exposure, the ratios get worse—16
to 1 for white women, 5 to 1 for Hispanic
women, and only 1.5 to 1 for Asian women,
meaning that the devastating fractures prevented
and caused in Asian women are nearly comparable.
A nationwide survey of resident physicians
found that knowledge regarding osteoporosis
diagnosis and treatment was poor, with a
particularly striking lack of knowledge
regarding the serious drug side effects. The
good news is that after stopping the drugs,
the risk of femur fracture rapidly dropped by
70% within a year, leading to the suggestion
that a drug holiday be considered after a few
years on the drug to help mediate the risk.
How crazy is that atypical femur fracture data,
right? I just cannot get over the irony of it all.
Okay, so between the lack of sufficient efficacy
and these rare but devastating side effects,
what can we do personally and how can we counsel
our patients to protect their skeletons? In 12
short years, government panels have gone from
suggesting widespread calcium supplementation
may be necessary to protect our bones
to "do not supplement." What happened?
It all started with a 2008 study in New
Zealand. Short-term studies had shown that
calcium supplementation may drop blood pressure
by about a point. The effect appears transient,
disappearing after a few months—better than
nothing. And excess calcium in the gut can
cause fat malabsorption by forming soap
fat, reducing saturated fat absorption,
and increasing fecal saturated fat content.
And indeed, if you take a couple Tums along
with your half bucket of KFC, up to twice
as much fat could end up in your stool.
And with less saturated fat absorbed into
your system, your cholesterol might drop.
So, the New Zealand researchers were expecting
to lower heart attack rates by giving women
calcium supplements. To their surprise, there
appeared to be more heart attacks in the calcium
supplement group. Was this just a fluke? All
eyes turned to the Women's Health Initiative,
the largest and longest randomized control
trial of calcium supplementation. The name
might sound familiar—that's the study
that uncovered how dangerous hormone
replacement therapy was. Would it
do the same for calcium supplements?
The Women's Health Initiative
reported no adverse effects. However,
the majority of participants were
already taking calcium supplements
before the study started. So effectively, the
study was just comparing higher versus lower
dose calcium supplementation, not calcium
supplements versus no calcium supplements.
What if you go back and just see what happened to
the women who started out not taking supplements
and then were randomized to the supplement
group? Those who started calcium supplements
suffered significantly more heart attacks
or strokes. Thus, high dose or low dose,
any calcium supplementation seems to
increase cardiovascular disease risk.
So, researchers went back digging through
other trial data for heart attack and stroke
rates in women randomized to calcium
supplements with or without vitamin D
added and confirmed the danger. And most
of the population studies agreed—users of
calcium supplements tended to have increased
rates of heart disease, stroke, and death.
The supplement industry was not happy,
accusing the researchers of relying in part
on self-reported data—like they just asked
people if they had a heart attack or not,
rather than verifying it. And indeed, long-term
calcium supplementation causes all sorts of
gastrointestinal distress, including twice the
risk of being hospitalized with acute symptoms
that may have been confused with a heart
attack. But no, the increased risk was seen
consistently across the trials, whether
the heart attacks were verified or not.
Okay, but why do calcium supplements increase
heart attack risk but not calcium you get in
your diet? Perhaps because when you take
calcium pills, you get a spike of calcium
in your bloodstream that you don't get just
eating calcium-rich foods. Within hours of
taking supplemental calcium, the calcium levels
in the blood shoot up and can stay up as long as
8 hours. This evidently produces what's called
a hypercoagulable state—your blood clots more
easily, which could increase the risk of
clots in the heart and brain. And indeed,
higher calcium blood levels are tied to
higher heart attack and stroke rates.
So, the mechanism may be calcium supplements
leading to unnaturally large, rapid,
and sustained calcium levels in the blood, which
can have a variety of potentially problematic
effects. Calcium supplements have been widely
embraced on the grounds that they are natural and
therefore a safe way of preventing osteoporosis
fractures. But it's now becoming clear that
taking calcium in one or two daily doses is not
natural and that it does not reproduce the same
metabolic effects as calcium in food the way
nature intended. And furthermore, the evidence
is also becoming steadily stronger that calcium
supplementation may not be safe. That's why most
organizations providing advice regarding
bone health now recommend that individuals
should obtain their calcium requirement
from diet in preference to supplements.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My latest book, “How Not to Age”
is out now,
which premiered at #2 on the
New York Times Best Sellers list.
Check it out at your
local public library.
Of course, all the proceeds
I receive of the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is itself a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads,
no corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.